Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 21: Physiology of Labor.
Maternal And Fetal Compartments Sex Steroid Hormone Role Prostaglandins Role PHASE 1: UTERINE QUIESCENCE AND CERVICAL SOFTENING PHASE 2: PREPARATION FOR LABOR PHASE 3: LABOR UTEROTONINS IN PARTURITION PHASE 3 PHASE 4: THE PUERPERIUM References.
Labor is characterized by forceful and painful uterine contractions that effect cervical dilation and cause the fetus to descend through the birth canal.
However, extensive preparations take place in both the uterus and cervix long before this.
During the first 36 to 38 weeks of normal gestation, the myometrium is in a preparatory yet unresponsive state.
Concurrently, the cervix begins an early stage of remodeling yet maintains structural integrity.
Following uterine quiescence, a transitional phase begins during which myometrial unresponsiveness is suspended and the cervix undergoes ripening, effacement, and loss of structural cohesion.
The physiological processes that regulate parturition and the onset of labor continue to be defined.
Three theories describe labor initiation.
Viewed simplistically, the first is the functional loss of pregnancy maintenance factors.
The second focuses on synthesis of factors that induce parturition.
The third suggests that the mature fetus is the source of the initial signal for parturition commencement.
Research supports a model that draws from all three themes.
Thus, labor onset represents the culmination of a series of biochemical changes in the uterus and cervix.
These result from endocrine and paracrine signals emanating from both mother and fetus.
Their relative contributions vary between species, and it is these differences that complicate elucidation of the exact factors that regulate human parturition.
When parturition is abnormal, preterm labor, dystocia, or postterm pregnancy may result.
Maternal And Fetal Compartments.
# Uterus and Cervix.
The myometrial layer of the uterus is composed of bundles of smooth muscle cells surrounded by connective tissue.
In contrast to skeletal or cardiac muscle, the smooth muscle cell is not terminally differentiated and therefore is readily adaptable to environmental changes.
Varied stimuli such as mechanical stretch, inflammation, and endocrine and paracrine signals modulate the transition of the smooth muscle cell into phenotypes that provide cell growth, proliferation, secretion, and contractility.
Additionally, several smooth muscle qualities confer advantages for uterine contraction efficiency and fetal delivery.
First, the degree of smooth muscle cell shortening with contractions may be one order of magnitude greater than that attained in striated muscle cells.
Second, forces can be exerted in smooth muscle cells in multiple directions.
This differs from the contraction force generated by skeletal muscle, which is always aligned with the axis of the muscle fibers.
Third, the thick and thin filaments of smooth muscle are found in long, random bundles throughout the cells.
This plexiform arrangement aids augmented shortening and force-generating capacity.
Last, greater multidirectional force generation in the uterine fundus compared with that of the lower uterine segment helps optimize expulsive force vectors.
Lining the thick muscular uterine walls, the endometrium is transformed by pregnancy hormones and is then termed decidua.
Composed of stromal cells and maternal immune cells, the decidua serves to maintain the pregnancy via unique immunoregulatory functions that suppress inflammatory signals during gestation.
However, at the end of pregnancy, the decidua transitions to induce inflammatory signals and withdraw active immunosuppression, contributing to parturition initiation.
During pregnancy, the cervix has multiple functions that include: (1) maintaining the epithelial barrier to protect the reproductive tract from infection, (2) sustaining cervical competence despite greater gravitational forces as the fetus grows, and (3) orchestrating extracellular matrix (ECM) changes that allow progressively greater tissue compliance.
In nonpregnant
women, the cervix is closed and firm, and its consistency is similar to nasal cartilage.
By the end of pregnancy, the cervix is easily distensible, and its consistency is similar to the lips of the oral cavity.
The cervix has a high ratio of fibroblasts to smooth muscle cells, and ECM contributes significantly to overall tissue mass.
Vink and colleagues (2016) showed that the smooth muscle cells in the cervix have a spatial gradient.
Specifically, smooth muscle cells make up approximately 50 percent of stromal cells at the internal os but only 10 percent at the external os.
Also, three-dimensional sonography and magnetic resonance imaging show increases in the cross-sectional area of the cervical canal and changes in ECM structure from early to late pregnancy (House, 2009; Lang, 2010; Pizzella, 2020).
Concurrent with expansion of the stroma, the cervical epithelia proliferate and exert a pregnancy-specific immunoprotection.
# Placenta.
In addition to providing the exchange of nutrients and waste between mother and fetus, the placenta is a key source of steroid hormones, growth factors, and other mediators that maintain pregnancy and potentially aid the transition to parturition.
The fetal membranes—amnion and chorion—and adjacent decidua serve as a physiologic, immunologic, and metabolic shield to protect against untimely parturition initiation.
The amnion provides virtually all of the fetal membranes’ tensile strength to resist membrane tearing and rupture .
This avascular tissue is highly resistant to penetration by leukocytes, microorganisms, and neoplastic cells .
It also constitutes a selective filter to prevent fetal particulate-bound lung and skin secretions from reaching the maternal compartment.
In this manner, maternal tissues are protected from amnionic fluid constituents that could prematurely accelerate decidual or myometrial activation or could promote adverse events such as amnionic fluid embolism.
Figure 21-1.
The amnion synthesizes prostaglandins, and late in pregnancy, synthesis is augmented by increased phospholipase A2 and prostaglandin H synthase, type 2 (PGHS-2) activity.
The transport of prostaglandins from the amnion to maternal tissues is limited by expression of the inactivating enzyme, prostaglandin dehydrogenase (PGDH), in the chorion.
During labor, PGDH levels decline, and amnion-derived prostaglandins can influence membrane rupture and uterine contractility.
The role of decidual activation in parturition is unclear but may involve local progesterone metabolism and higher prostaglandin receptor concentrations, thus enhancing uterine prostaglandin actions and cytokine production.
Redrawn from Smith R: Parturition.
N Engl J Med. 2007 Jan 18;356(3):271–283.
The chorion is a primarily protective tissue layer and provides immunological acceptance.
It is also enriched with enzymes that inactivate uterotonins, which are agents that stimulate contractions.
Inactivating enzymes include prostaglandin dehydrogenase, oxytocinase, and enkephalinase (Cheung, 1990; Germain, 1994; Mizutani, 2011).
Sex Steroid Hormone Role.
In many species, the role of sex steroid hormones is clear— estrogen promotes and progesterone inhibits the events leading to parturition.
The removal of progesterone, that is, progesterone withdrawal, directly precedes progression of parturition.
In addition, providing progesterone to some species will delay parturition via a decline in myometrial activity and continued cervical competency .
In humans, however, both estrogen and progesterone are components of a broader molecular system that maintains uterine quiescence.
Plasma levels of estrogen and progesterone in normal pregnancy are enormous and in great excess of the affinity constants for their receptors.
For this reason, it is difficult to comprehend how relatively subtle changes in the ratio of their concentrations could modulate physiological processes during pregnancy.
The evidence, however, for an increased progesterone-toestrogen ratio in the maintenance of pregnancy and a decline in this ratio for parturition is
overwhelming.
In all species studied, including humans, administration of the progesterone-receptor antagonists mifepristone (RU486) or onapristone will promote some or all key features of parturition.
These include cervical ripening, greater cervical distensibility, and augmented uterine sensitivity to uterotonins (Bygdeman, 1994; Chwalisz, 1994b; Wolf, 1993).
The exact role of estrogen in regulation of human uterine quiescence and cervical competency is less well understood.
That said, estrogen can advance progesterone responsiveness and, at the end of pregnancy, aid in processes that mediate uterine activation and cervical ripening.
Both progesterone and estrogen bind to nuclear receptors that regulate gene transcription.
Two nuclear receptors for estrogen are estrogen receptor α (ERα) and estrogen receptor β (ERβ).
Nuclear receptor isoforms of the progesterone receptor (PR-A and PR-B) are encoded by differing transcripts from a single gene .
Prostaglandins Role.
Prostaglandins are lipid molecules with varied hormone-like actions.
In parturition, they play a prominent role in myometrial contractility, relaxation, and inflammation.
Prostaglandins interact with a family of eight different G protein–coupled receptors (p. 403), several of which are expressed in the myometrium and the cervix (Konopka, 2015; Myatt, 2004).
The major synthetic pathway involved in prostaglandin biosynthesis is shown in Figure 21-2.
Prostaglandins are produced using plasma membrane– derived arachidonic acid, which usually is released by the action of phospholipase A2 or C.
The enzymes type 1 and 2 prostaglandin H synthase (PGHS-1 and -2), also known as cyclooxygenase 1 and 2 (COX-1 and -2), convert arachidonic acid to prostaglandin H2 (PGH2).
These enzymes are the target of many nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).
The tocolytic actions of specific COX inhibitors, as discussed in Chapter 45 (p. 806), were considered promising until they were shown to have adverse fetal effects (Loudon, 2003; Olson, 2007).
Figure 21-2.
Overview of the prostaglandin biosynthetic pathway.
PG = prostaglandin; PGDH = prostaglandin dehydrogenase; PGE2 = prostaglandin E2; PGF2α = prostaglandin F2α; PGH2 = prostaglandin H2; PGHS = prostaglandin H synthase; PGI2 = prostaglandin I2; PLA2 = phospholipase A2; PLC = phospholipase C.
Through prostaglandin isomerases, PGH2 is converted to active prostaglandins.
These include prostaglandins E2 (PGE2), F2α (PGF2α), and I2 (PGI2).
Isomerase expression is tissue-specific and thereby controls the relative production of various prostaglandins.
Another important control point for prostaglandin activity is its metabolism, which most often is through the action of 15-hydroxyprostaglandin dehydrogenase (PGDH).
Expression of this enzyme is upregulated during pregnancy in the uterus and cervix, which provides the important ability to rapidly inactivate prostaglandins (Giannoulias, 2002; Kishore, 2017).
Thus, myometrial responses to prostaglandins stem from a balance between prostaglandin synthesis versus metabolism, from the relative expression of various prostaglandin receptors, or from a switch in receptor-signaling pathways (Kandola, 2014; Lyall, 2002; Olson, 2007; Smith, 2001).
It is possible that prostanoids contribute to myometrial relaxation at one stage of pregnancy and to myometrial contractions after parturition initiation .
In addition to the myometrium, the amnion synthesizes several bioactive peptides and prostaglandins that cause myometrial relaxation or contraction (see Fig. 21-1).
Late in pregnancy, amnionic prostaglandin biosynthesis of PGE2 and PGF2α is increased, and phospholipase A2 and PGHS-2 show greater activity .
The amnion is likely the major source for amnionic fluid prostaglandins, and their role in the activation of cascades that promote membrane rupture is clear.
However, the influence of amnionderived prostaglandins on uterine quiescence and activation is less clear because their access to maternal tissues is limited by expression of PGDH.
PHASE 1: UTERINE QUIESCENCE AND CERVICAL
Softening.
Parturition can be arbitrarily divided into four overlapping phases that correspond to the major physiological transitions of the myometrium and cervix during pregnancy (Casey, 1997; Shynlova, 2020; Vink, 2018).
These include: (1) the prelude, (2) the preparation, (3) the process itself, and (4) the recovery.
Importantly, the phases of parturition should not be confused with the clinical stages of labor.
The first, second, and third stages of labor make up phase 3 of parturition .
Figure 21-3.
The phases of parturition.
Figure 21-4.
Labor course divided on the basis of expected evolution of the dilatation and descent curves into three functional divisions.
The preparatory division includes the latent and active phases.
The dilatational division is the phase of maximum slope of dilatation.
The pelvic division encompasses both the deceleration phase and the second stage, which is concurrent with the phase of maximum slope of fetal descent.
Redrawn from Friedman EA: Labor: Clinical Evaluation and Management, 2nd ed.
New York, Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1978.
Beginning even before implantation, a remarkably effective period of myometrial quiescence is imposed.
This phase 1 normally constitutes 95 percent of pregnancy and is characterized by uterine smooth muscle tranquility with maintenance of cervical structural integrity .
All manner of molecular systems—neural, endocrine, paracrine, and autocrine— are likely called to implement and coordinate a state of relative uterine unresponsiveness.
Moreover, a complementary “fail-safe” system that protects the uterus against agents that could perturb the tranquility of phase 1 also must be in place.
Figure 21-5.
The key factors thought to regulate the phases of human parturition.
CRH = corticotropin-releasing hormone; hCG = human chorionic gonadotropin; PAF = platelet-activating factor; PGDH = prostaglandin dehydrogenase; SPA = surfactant protein A.
During phase 1, the uterus must initiate extensive changes in its size and vascularity to accommodate fetal growth.
Concurrently, myometrial cells undergo a phenotypic modification to a noncontractile state, and uterine muscle is rendered unresponsive to natural stimuli.
Although this unresponsiveness continues until near the end of pregnancy, some lowintensity myometrial contractions are felt during the quiescent phase.
These contractions do not normally cause cervical dilation, and they are common toward the end of pregnancy, especially in multiparas.
They are referred to as Braxton Hicks contractions or false labor .
The quiescence of phase 1 likely stems from: (1) actions of estrogen and progesterone via intracellular receptors, (2) myometrial-cell plasma membrane receptor–mediated increases in cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP), (3) generation of cyclic guanosine monophosphate, and (4) other systems, including modification of myometrial-cell ion channels.
# Myometrial Relaxation and Contraction.
The balance between myometrial relaxation and contraction is controlled by steroid- and peptide-hormone transcriptional regulation of key genes and their protein products .
Quiescence is achieved in part by: (1) diminished intracellular crosstalk and reduced intracellular Ca2+ ([Ca2+]i) levels, (2) ion-channel regulation of cell membrane potential, (3) activation of the stress–unfolded protein response by the uterine endoplasmic reticulum, and (4) uterotonin degradation.
In contrast, contractility results from: (1) enhanced interactions between the actin and myosin proteins, (2) heightened excitability of individual myometrial cells, and (3) promotion of intracellular crosstalk that allows synchronous contractions to develop.
Actin–Myosin Interactions Actin and myosin proteins are essential to muscle contraction.
For this, actin must be converted from a globular to a filamentous form.
Indeed, a potential mechanism for maintenance of relaxation is the promotion of actin into a globular form rather than into fibrils, which are required for contraction.
Moreover, actin must be attached to the cytoskeleton at focal
points in the cell membrane to allow tension to develop.
Actin must partner with myosin, which is composed of multiple light and heavy chains .
This interaction is brought about by enzymatic phosphorylation of the 20-kDa light chain of myosin .
This is catalyzed by the enzyme myosin light-chain kinase, which is activated by calcium (Ca2+).
Figure 21-6.
Uterine myocyte relaxation and contraction.
A. Uterine relaxation is maintained by factors that increase myocyte cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) levels.
This activates protein kinase A (PKA) to promote phosphodiesterase activity with dephosphorylation of myosin light-chain kinase (MLCK).
Other processes serve to maintain actin in a globular form and thus to prevent the fibril formation necessary for contractions.
B. Uterine contractions result from reversal of these sequences.
Actin now assumes a fibrillar form, and calcium enters the cell to combine with calmodulin to form complexes.
These complexes activate MLCK to bring about phosphorylation of the myosin light chains.
This generates ATPase activity to cause sliding of myosin over the actin fibrils, which is a uterine contraction.
AC = adenylyl cyclase; Ca2+ = calcium; DAG = diacylglycerol; Gs and Gα = G-receptor proteins; IP 3 = inositol triphosphate; LC20 = light chain 20; PIP 3 = phosphatidylinositol 3,4,5– triphosphate; PLC = phospholipase C; R-PKA = inactive protein kinase.
Redrawn from Smith R: Parturition.
N Engl J Med. 2007 Jan 18;356(3):271–283.
Thus, logically, uterine relaxation ordinarily is promoted by conditions that lower concentrations of (Ca2+)i.
In contrast, agents that prompt contraction act on myometrial cells to augment (Ca2+)i levels.
Or, they allow an influx of extracellular calcium through ligand- or voltage-regulated calcium channels (see Fig. 21-6).
For example, PGF2α and oxytocin bind their respective receptors during labor to open ligand-activated calcium channels.
Activation of these receptors also releases calcium from the sarcoplasmic reticulum.
Additionally, greater localization of nonselective cation channels on the cell membrane promotes Ca2+ entry .
The rise in (Ca2+)i levels is often transient.
But, contractions can be prolonged by inhibition of myosin phosphatase, an enzyme that dephosphorylates myosin .
Regulation of Membrane Potentials As just noted, myocyte excitability is regulated in part by changes in the electrochemical potential gradient across the plasma membrane.
Before labor, myocytes maintain a relatively high interior electronegativity.
Maintenance of a hyperpolarized membrane potential attenuates smooth muscle cell excitation and is regulated by ion channels.
Numerous ion channels control sodium (Na+) and calcium (Ca2+) influx and potassium (K+) efflux to collectively regulate membrane potential.
Sodium leak channels (NALCN) are important to normal uterine function .
Another key regulator is the large-conductance voltage- and Ca2+-activated K+ channel (BKCa) (Pérez, 1993).
The BKCa channel is abundantly expressed in the myometrium and plays dual promoting and opposing roles to maintain a balance between uterine quiescence and contractility.
Opening the BKCa channel allows potassium to leave the cell to maintain interior electronegativity, thus preventing voltage-gated Ca2+ influx and contraction.
Inhibition of the BKCa channel augments myometrial contractility.
Regulation of uterine contractility from early to late gestation may result from temporal changes in expression of the BKCa channel and/or BKCa interacting partners .
Myometrial Gap Junctions Cellular signals that control myometrial contraction and relaxation can be effectively transferred between cells through intercellular junctional channels.
Communication is established between myocytes by gap junctions, which aid the passage of electrical or ionic coupling currents as well as metabolite coupling.
The connexin family of proteins form cell-type specific gap junctions .
Connexin-43 is expressed in the myometrium, and concentrations rise near labor onset.
Six connexin subunits form a connexon,
and two adjacent connexons establish a conduit between communicating cells.
This permits exchange of small molecules that can be nutrients, waste, metabolites, second messengers, or ions.
Optimal numbers and types of gap junctions are believed to be important for electrical myometrial synchrony.
Progesterone promotes uterine quiescence in part by lowering expression of contraction-associated proteins (CAPs) and maintaining expression of anticontractile agents such as caspase 3 (Ingles, 2018; Kyathanahalli, 2015).
CAPs include the oxytocin receptor, prostaglandin F receptor, and connexin43.
Also, at the end of pregnancy, increased stretch, metabolism of progesterone by the enzyme 20α-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase (20α-HSD), loss of progesterone-mediated repression of CAP genes, and greater estrogen dominance raise CAP levels.
Integration of diverse regulatory pathways culminates in released inhibition of connexin-43 and oxytocin receptor levels to promote greater uterine contractility (Anamthathmakula, 2019; Mendelson, 2019; Peavey, 2021).
G Protein–Coupled Receptors In addition to ion-channel linked receptors, G protein–coupled receptors regulate myocyte contractility.
These receptors together with appropriate ligands may act with sex steroid hormones to maintain uterine quiescence (Price, 2000; Sanborn, 1998).
Examples are the luteinizing hormone (LH) receptor and corticotropin-releasing hormone receptor 1 (CRHR1), both described in this section .
Other G protein–coupled myometrial receptors, instead, are associated with uterine contractility.
G protein– mediated activation of phospholipase C, which releases arachidonic acid, is one example.
Ligands for the G protein–coupled receptors include numerous neuropeptides, hormones, and autacoids.
Many of these are available to the myometrium during pregnancy in high concentration via endocrine or autocrine mechanisms.
Figure 21-7.
G protein–coupled receptor signal transduction pathways.
A. Receptors coupled to heterotrimeric guanosine-triphosphate (GTP)-binding proteins (G proteins) are integral transmembrane proteins that transduce extracellular signals to the cell interior.
G protein–coupled receptors exhibit a common structural motif consisting of seven membrane-spanning regions.
B. Receptor occupation promotes interaction between the receptor and the G protein on the interior surface of the membrane.
An exchange of guanosine diphosphate (GDP) for GTP on the G protein α subunit and dissociation of the α subunit from the βγ heterodimer occurs.
Depending on its isoform, the GTP-α subunit complex mediates intracellular signaling either indirectly by acting on effector molecules such as adenylyl cyclase (AC) or phospholipase C (PLC), or directly by regulating ion channel or kinase function.
cAMP = cyclic adenosine monophosphate; DAG = diacylglycerol; IP 3 = inositol triphosphate.
LH and human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) hormones share the same LH-hCG receptor.
This G protein–coupled receptor is found in myometrial smooth muscle and blood vessels, and levels during pregnancy are greater before labor .
hCG acts to activate adenylyl cyclase by way of a plasma membrane receptor Gαs-linked system.
This lessens contraction frequency and force and lowers the number of tissue-specific myometrial cell gap junctions (Ambrus, 1994; Eta, 1994).
Thus, high circulating levels of hCG may be one mechanism of uterine quiescence.
β-Adrenergic receptors mediate Gαs-stimulated myometrial cell relaxation.
Agents binding to these receptors have been used for tocolysis of preterm labor and include ritodrine and terbutaline .
The rate-limiting factor is likely the number of receptors expressed and the level of adenylyl cyclase expression.
Prostaglandin E2 mediates its diverse cellular effects through four G protein–coupled receptors.
Specifically, prostaglandin E receptors 1 through 4 (EP1-EP4) are expressed in the myometrium during pregnancy and with labor onset (Astle, 2005; Leonhardt, 2003).
EP2 and EP4 act through Gαs to maintain myometrial cell quiescence but
switch to a Gαq/11 calciumactivating pathway during labor .
EP1 and EP3 receptors act through Gαq and Gαi to augment intracellular Ca2+ and contractility.
The peptide hormone relaxin binds to the G protein–coupled receptor named relaxin family peptide receptor 1 (RXFP1).
Binding activates adenylyl cyclase, which in turn prevents increased intracellular Ca2+, and thus promotes uterine quiescence (Downing, 1993; Meera, 1995).
The H1 relaxin gene is primarily expressed in the decidua, trophoblast, and prostate, whereas the H2 gene is primarily expressed in the corpus luteum.
Relaxin plasma levels peak at approximately 1 ng/mL between 8 and 12 weeks’ gestation.
Thereafter, they decline until term.
Corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) is synthesized in the placenta and hypothalamus.
Discussed on page 408, CRH plasma levels rise dramatically during the final 6 to 8 weeks of normal pregnancy and are implicated in mechanisms that control the timing of human parturition (Smith, 2007; Wadhwa, 1998; Wang, 2019).
CRH appears to promote myometrial quiescence during most of pregnancy but then aids contractions with parturition onset.
Studies suggest that these opposing actions are achieved by differential actions of CRH via its receptor CRHR1.
In nonlaboring myometrium at term, the interaction of CRH with CRHR1 activates the Gsadenylate cyclase-cAMP signaling pathway.
This results in inhibition of inositol triphosphate (IP3) and stabilization of (Ca2+)i levels .
However, in term laboring myometrium, (Ca2+)i concentrations are augmented by CRH activation of G proteins Gq and Gi and prompts stimulation of IP3 production and greater contractility.
Cyclic Guanosine Monophosphate As noted, cAMP is an important mediator of myometrial relaxation.
However, activation of guanylyl cyclase raises intracellular cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP) levels.
This also promotes smooth muscle relaxation .
Intracellular cGMP levels are increased in the pregnant myometrium and can be stimulated by atrial natriuretic peptide, brain natriuretic peptide, and nitric oxide (Guerra, 2019; Telfer, 2001).
All of these factors and their receptors are expressed in the pregnant uterus.
Accelerated Uterotonin Degradation The activity of enzymes that degrade or inactivate endogenously produced uterotonins also is strikingly increased in phase 1.
Pairs of some degrading enzymes and their respective targets include PGDH and prostaglandins; enkephalinase and endothelins; oxytocinase and oxytocin; diamine oxidase and histamine; catechol O-methyltransferase and catecholamines; angiotensinases and angiotensin II; and platelet-activating factor (PAF) and PAF acetylhydrolase.
Levels of several of these enzymes decline late in gestation .
# Decidua.
To ensure uterine quiescence, the synthesis in the decidua of prostaglandins, in particular PGF2α, is markedly suppressed.
Suppression of prostaglandin production here persists throughout most of pregnancy, and suppression withdrawal is a prerequisite for parturition .
The mother and fetus come in direct contact at the decidua basalis and decidua parietalis.
At this interface, myeloid and lymphoid immune cells such as natural killer cells, macrophages, dendritic cells, and T cells undergo dynamic changes in number and phenotype to achieve a balanced microenvironment (Ander, 2019; Solano, 2019; van der Zwan, 2020).
This is a critical site for immune tolerance in phase 1 and for decidual activation in phase 2 of parturition (see Fig. 21-5).
In phase 1 of parturition, these cells, in collaboration with decidual cells, promote an environment of immune tolerance to protect the fetus.
Immune cells with innate and adaptive immune responses support vascular and tissue remodeling, immune surveillance and defense, and trophoblast invasion in phase 1 .
Figure 21-8.
Immune tolerance and activation at the maternal fetal interface.
In the antepartum period, dNK cells are abundant and their maturation is promoted by release of uterine IL-15.
These cells promote decidual remodeling, blastocyst implantation, and EVT invasion.
The
cytotoxicity of dNK cells is regulated by the interaction of its KIR receptor with HLA-G on EVTs.
Decidual macrophages— primary antigen-presenting cells—produce the enzyme IDO, which limits T cell activation.
Changes in the intrapartum period are less understood, but the number of dNK cells decline and decidual macrophages are activated to a proinflammatory phenotype.
dNK = decidual natural killer; EVT = extravillous trophoblasts; HLA = human leukocyte antigen; IL = interleukin; IDO = indoleamine 2,3dioxygenase; KIR = killer-cell immunoglobulin-like receptors.
During phase 2, decidual stromal cells and fetal membranes undergo an aging process termed cellular senescence.
Noninflammatory signals precipitate senescence, which in turn leads to synthesis of proinflammatory cytokines, augmented prostaglandin production, and increased protease expression.
These proteins and hormones break down fetal membranes.
# Cervical Softening.
The initial stage of cervical remodeling—termed softening—begins in phase 1 of parturition.
It is characterized by greater tissue compliance, yet the cervix remains firm and unyielding.
Hegar (1895) first described palpable softening of the lower uterine segment at 4 to 6 weeks’ gestation, and this sign was once used to diagnose pregnancy.
Clinically, the maintenance of cervical anatomical and structural integrity is essential for pregnancy to continue to term.
Preterm cervical dilation, structural insufficiency, or both may forecast delivery.
# Cervical Connective Tissue.
Cervical softening is an active molecular process that balances tissue competence against slow, progressive compositional and structural changes in the extracellular matrix (ECM) to increase compliance (Myers, 2015; Nallasamy, 2017; Vink, 2018).
Constituents of the ECM include type I and III fibrillar collagens, matricellular proteins, glycosaminoglycans, proteoglycans, and elastic fibers.
Key to matrix changes, collagen, which is the main structural protein in the cervix, undergoes conformational changes that alter tissue stiffness and flexibility .
Specifically, collagen processing and the number or type of stable covalent cross-links between collagen’s triple helices are altered.
Beginning in early pregnancy, mature cross-links between newly synthesized collagen monomers are reduced due to diminished expression and activity of the cross-link-forming enzymes (Akins, 2011; Yoshida, 2014).
These enzymes are lysyl hydroxylase and lysyl oxidase.
Gradual turnover of collagen during pregnancy replaces mature cross-linked collagen fibrils with poorly linked fibrils.
The result is a collagen with reduced stiffness.
The collagen-binding proteoglycans— decorin and biglycan—ensure the new, poorly cross-linked collagen is appropriately assembled and deposited in the ECM.
Data from human and mouse studies support the theory that a balance in the synthesis and breakdown of collagen, rather than loss of collagen, achieves cervical remodeling (Akins, 2011; Myers, 2008; Read, 2007; Yoshida, 2014).
Figure 21-9.
Mouse studies identify molecular changes in collagen structure and function during cervical remodeling.
These changes are regulated by steroid hormones and result in a gradual loss of tissue stiffness.
During the softening phase, the decline in lysyl oxidase activity in conjunction with high collagen turnover results in the replacement of strong cross-linked collagen fibers with weakly crosslinked collagen fibers.
Second harmonic generation images in the mouse and human cervix show the corresponding gradual decline in mechanical function of the cervix.
Compiled from Akins, 2010, 2011; Ozasa, 1981; Read, 2007; Yoshida, 2014; Zhang, 2012.
Clinical evidence for the importance of matrix changes to cervical softening is supported by in vivo mechanical evaluation of the cervix (Badir, 2013; Parra-Saavedra, 2011).
The prevalence of cervical insufficiency is also higher in those with inherited defects in the synthesis or assembly of collagen or elastic fibers (Anum, 2009; Hermanns-Le, 2005; Volozonoka, 2020).
Examples are
Ehlers-Danlos and Marfan syndromes, discussed in Chapter 62 (p. 1121).
Concurrent with matrix remodeling in the softening period, genes involved in cervical dilation and parturition are actively repressed .
PHASE 2: PREPARATION FOR LABOR To prepare for labor, the myometrial tranquility of phase 1 of parturition must be suspended.
This so-called uterine awakening or activation in phase 2 of parturition is a progression of uterine changes during the last few weeks of pregnancy.
Importantly, shifting events associated with phase 2 can cause either preterm or delayed labor.
# Progesterone Withdrawal.
Key factors in uterine activation are depicted in Figure 21-5.
In species that exhibit progesterone withdrawal, parturition progression to labor can be blocked by administering progesterone to the mother.
Whether progesterone administration in the absence of classic progesterone withdrawal can delay the timely onset of parturition or prevent preterm labor remains unclear.
The possibility that progesterone may prevent preterm labor has been studied, but its use in preventing preterm birth continues to be debated .
Classic progesterone withdrawal from decreased secretion does not occur in human parturition.
However, a mechanism for progesterone inactivation, whereby the myometrium and cervix become refractory to progesterone’s inhibitory actions, is supported by studies using progesteronereceptor antagonists.
Mifepristone is a classic steroid antagonist, acting at the level of the progesterone receptor.
Although less effective in inducing abortion or labor later in pregnancy, mifepristone appears to have some effect on cervical ripening and on increasing myometrial sensitivity to uterotonins (Berkane, 2005; Chwalisz, 1994a).
The diverse mechanisms by which functional progesterone withdrawal or antagonism is achieved is an active area of research.
These include: (1) changes in the relative expression of the nuclear progesterone-receptor (PR) isoforms, (2) differential interaction of PR isoforms A and B with enhancers and inhibitors of gene expression, (3) altered PR activity through changes in the expression of coactivators or corepressors of receptor function, (4) local progesterone inactivation by steroid-metabolizing enzymes or synthesis of a natural antagonist, and (5) microRNA regulation of progesteronemetabolizing enzymes and
transcription factors that modulate uterine quiescence (Chen, 2017; Condon, 2003; Mahendroo, 1999; Mesiano, 2002; Nadeem, 2016; Peavey, 2021; Renthal, 2010; Williams, 2012).
Thus, multiple pathways exist to create functional progesterone withdrawal.
# Myometrial Changes.
Phase 2 changes in the myometrium prepare it for labor contractions.
Changes result from a shift in the expression of proteins that control uterine quiescence to an expression of CAPs, described earlier (p. 403) (Mendelson, 2019; Renthal, 2015; Stanfield, 2019).
These CAPs increase uterine responsiveness to uterotonins.
Another critical change in phase 2 is formation of the lower uterine segment from the isthmus.
With this development, the fetal head often descends to or even through the pelvic inlet—lightening.
The abdomen commonly undergoes a shape change, sometimes described by women as “the baby dropped.
It is also likely that the lower segment myometrium is unique from that in the upper uterine segment, and leads to distinct roles for each near term and during labor.
This is supported by human studies that demonstrate differential expression of prostaglandin receptors and CAPs within the upper- and lower-segment myometrial regions (Astle, 2005; Blanks, 2003; Sparey, 1999).
Near term, elevated expression of the HoxA13 gene in the lower myometrial segment compared with the upper segment also induces CAP expression and regionalized contractility of the lower segment .
Oxytocin Receptors Because of its long-standing application for labor induction, it seemed logical that oxytocin must play a central role in spontaneous human labor.
Myometrial oxytocin receptor levels do rise during phase 2 of parturition, and the level of
oxytocin receptor mRNA in human myometrium at term is greater than that found in preterm myometrium .
However, it is unclear whether oxytocin plays a role in the early phases of uterine activation or whether its sole function is in the expulsive phase of labor.
Most studies of regulation of myometrial oxytocin receptor synthesis have been performed in rodents.
Disruption of the oxytocin receptor gene in the mouse does not affect parturition.
This suggests that, at least in this species, multiple systems likely ensure that parturition occurs.
Progesterone inhibits and estradiol induces oxytocin receptor expression.
Through interaction with PR-B, progesterone regulates numerous genes in the oxytocin signaling pathway .
Progesterone may also act within the myometrial cell to enhance oxytocin receptor degradation .
These data indicate that one of the mechanisms whereby progesterone maintains uterine quiescence is through inhibition of a myometrial oxytocin signaling pathway.
# Cervical Ripening.
Before contractions begin, the cervix must shift from a state of competence to one of compliance.
This eventually leads to the cervix yielding and dilating from forceful uterine contractions.
Cervical modifications during phase 2 principally involve connective tissue changes—termed cervical ripening.
The transition from the softening to the ripening phase begins weeks or days before labor.
The understanding of this cervical matrix transformation remains incomplete.
However, it is clear that levels of glycosaminoglycans, which are large linear polysaccharides, are uniquely increased in phase 2.
Glycosaminoglycans and Proteoglycans Hyaluronan is a high-molecular-weight polysaccharide that functions alone, but most other glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) complex with proteins to form proteoglycans.
Hyaluronan is a hydrophilic, space-filling molecule, and thus greater hyaluronan production during cervical ripening is thought to increase viscoelasticity, hydration, and matrix disorganization.
Hyaluronan synthesis is carried out by hyaluronan synthase isoenzymes, and expression of these enzymes is elevated in the cervix during ripening (Akgul, 2012; Straach, 2005).
Inflammatory Changes In phase 2, resident immune cells are localized to the cervical stroma, although a functional role for them in this phase has not been demonstrated.
For example, studies of gene expression patterns at term both before and after cervical ripening show little rise in proinflammatory gene expression.
However, once labor is underway, activation of neutrophils, proinflammatory M1 macrophages, and tissue repair M2 macrophages in the cervix is augmented.
Moreover, proinflammatory and immunosuppressive gene expression in the cervix increases markedly after delivery (Bollapragada, 2009; Hassan, 2006, 2009).
This suggests a role for inflammatory cells in postpartum cervical remodeling and repair .
Induction of Cervical Ripening No therapies prevent premature cervical ripening.
In contrast, treatment to promote cervical ripening for labor induction includes direct application of PGE2 and PGF2α .
Prostaglandins likely modify ECM structure to aid ripening, although their role in the normal physiology of cervical ripening remains unclear.
In some nonhuman species, events that allow cervical ripening are induced by dropping serum progesterone concentrations.
And in humans, administration of progesterone antagonists causes cervical ripening.
Endocervical Epithelia In addition to matrix changes during pregnancy, endocervical epithelial cells proliferate such that endocervical glands account for a significant percentage of cervical mass.
The endocervical canal is lined with mucus-secreting columnar and stratified squamous epithelia.
These cells form both a mucosal barrier and a tight junctional barrier that protect against microbial invasion (Akgul, 2014; Blaskewicz, 2011; Timmons, 2007).
The mucosal epithelium recognizes and deters pathogen invasion via expression of toll-like receptors that identify pathogens and via antimicrobial peptides and protease inhibitors.
These
epithelia also express signals to underlying immune cells when a pathogenic challenge exceeds their protective capacity .
# Fetal Contributions to Parturition.
It is intriguing to envision that the mature human fetus provides the signal to initiate parturition, and evidence for fetal signaling is mounting .
The fetus may give signals through blood-borne agents that act on the placenta or through secretion into the amnionic fluid.
Uterine Stretch Fetal growth is an important component of uterine activation in phase 2 of parturition.
With uterine activation, stretch is required for induction of specific CAPs.
Namely, stretch increases expression of connexin-43 and oxytocin receptors.
Levels of gastrin-releasing peptide, a stimulatory agonist for smooth muscle, also are augmented by stretch in the myometrium .
Clinical clues for a role of stretch come from the observation that multifetal pregnancies carry a much greater risk for preterm labor than singleton ones.
Preterm labor is also more common in pregnancies complicated by hydramnios.
Although the mechanisms causing preterm birth in these two are debated, a role for uterine stretch must be considered.
Cell signaling systems are influenced by stretch to regulate the myometrial cell.
This process—mechanotransduction—may include activation of cell-surface receptors or ion channels, transmission of signals through ECM, or release of autocrine molecules that act directly on myometrium (Shynlova, 2007; Young, 2011).
Fetal Endocrine Cascades The ability of the fetus to provide endocrine signals that initiate parturition has been demonstrated in several species.
However, evidence suggests that it is not regulated in the same manner in humans.
That said, the human fetal hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal-placental axis is considered a critical component of normal parturition.
Moreover, premature activation of this axis is considered to prompt many cases of preterm labor (Challis, 2000, 2001).
Steroid products of the human fetal adrenal gland are believed to have effects on the placenta and membranes that eventually transform the myometrium from a quiescent to a contractile state.
A key component in the human may be the unique ability of the placenta to produce large amounts of CRH that is identical to maternal and fetal hypothalamic CRH (Grino, 1987; Saijonmaa, 1988) .
However, unlike hypothalamic CRH, which is under glucocorticoid negative feedback, cortisol instead stimulates placental CRH production.
This ability makes it possible to create a feed-forward endocrine cascade that does not end until delivery.
Figure 21-10.
The placental–fetal adrenal endocrine cascade.
In late gestation, placental corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) stimulates fetal adrenal production of dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate (DHEA-S) and cortisol.
The latter stimulates production of placental CRH, which leads to a feed-forward cascade that enhances adrenal steroid hormone production.
ACTH = adrenocorticotropic hormone.
Maternal plasma CRH levels are low in the first trimester and rise from midgestation to term.
In the last 12 weeks, CRH plasma levels rise exponentially, peak during labor, and then fall precipitously after delivery (Frim, 1988; Sasaki, 1987).
Amnionic fluid CRH concentrations similarly increase in late gestation.
CRH is the only trophic hormone-releasing factor to have a specific serum binding protein.
During most of pregnancy, CRHbinding protein (CRH-BP) binds most maternal circulating CRH, and this inactivates it .
During later pregnancy, however, CRH-BP levels in both maternal plasma and amnionic fluid decline, leading to markedly greater levels of bioavailable CRH (Perkins, 1995; Petraglia, 1997).
In pregnancies in which the fetus can be considered “stressed” from various complications, concentrations of CRH in fetal plasma, amnionic fluid, and maternal plasma are greater than those seen in normal gestation (Berkowitz, 1996; McGrath, 2002).
The placenta is the likely source of this elevated CRH concentration.
For example, placental CRH content is fourfold higher in
placentas from women with preeclampsia than in those from normal pregnancies .
Placental CRH is thought to play several roles in parturition regulation.
It may enhance fetal cortisol production to provide positive feedback so that the placenta produces more CRH.
Late in pregnancy—phase 2 or 3 of parturition—modification in the CRH receptor favors a switch from cAMP formation instead to increased myometrial cell calcium levels via protein kinase C activation .
Oxytocin acts to attenuate CRH-stimulated accumulation of cAMP in myometrial tissue.
CRH acts to augment myometrial contractile force in response to PGF2α .
Last, CRH stimulates fetal adrenal C19-steroid synthesis, thereby increasing substrate for placental aromatization.
Some have proposed that the rising CRH level at the end of gestation reflects a fetal-placental clock .
CRH concentrations vary greatly among women, and the rate of rise in maternal CRH levels is a more accurate predictor of pregnancy outcome than is a single measurement (Leung, 2001; McGrath, 2002).
In this regard, the placenta and fetus, through endocrinological events, influence parturition timing at the end of normal gestation.
Fetal Lung Surfactant and Platelet-activating Factor Surfactant protein A (SP-A) produced by the fetal lung is required for lung maturation.
SP-A is expressed by the human amnion and decidua, is present in the amnionic fluid, and prompts signaling pathways in human myometrial cells (Garcia-Verdugo, 2008; Lee, 2010; Snegovskikh, 2011).
The exact mechanisms by which SP-A activates myometrial contractility in women, however, remain to be clarified.
One mode may be its effects on prostaglandins.
Namely, SP-A selectively inhibits PGF2α in the term decidua, but SP-A levels drop in the amnionic fluid at term .
The fetal lung also makes the uterotonic agent platelet-activating factor (Frenkel, 1996; Toyoshima, 1995).
This factor and SP-A play a role in fetal– maternal signaling for parturition .
Fetal Membrane Senescence Toward the end of pregnancy, fetal membranes undergo cellular senescence .
In human and animal fetal membranes, stretch and oxidative stress induce senescent fetal membrane to manifest a form of sterile inflammation termed senescent-associated secretory phenotype (SASP).
This in turn propagates inflammatory signals that further weaken the fetal membrane and activate signals in the decidua and myometrium to initiate parturition.
Thus, as the functional necessity of fetal membranes declines at term, they are able to promote signals that contribute to parturition initiation.
Fetal Anomalies and Delayed Parturition Some evidence shows that pregnancies with markedly diminished estrogen production may be associated with prolonged gestation.
These include women with inherited placental sulfatase deficiency and fetal anencephaly with adrenal hypoplasia.
The broad range of gestational length seen with these disorders, however, calls into question the exact role of estrogen in human parturition initiation.
Some brain anomalies of the fetal calf, fetal lamb, and sometimes the human fetus delay the normal timing of parturition.
In particular, the association between fetal anencephaly and prolonged gestation is well described (Rea, 1898; Malpas, 1933).
Malpas concluded that the prolonged gestation was attributable to anomalous fetal brain-pituitary-adrenal function.
Indeed, the adrenal glands of the anencephalic fetus are very small and, at term, may be only 5 to 10 percent as large as those of a normal fetus.
This is caused by developmental failure of the fetal zone that normally accounts for most of fetal adrenal mass and production of C19-steroid hormones .
Such pregnancies are associated with delayed labor and suggest that the fetal adrenal glands are important for the timely onset of parturition.
Other fetal abnormalities that prevent or severely reduce the entry of fetal urine or lung secretions into amnionic fluid do not prolong human pregnancy.
Examples are renal agenesis and pulmonary hypoplasia, respectively.
Thus, a fetal signal through the paracrine arm
of the fetal–maternal communication system does not appear to be mandated for parturition initiation.
PHASE 3: LABOR This phase is synonymous with active labor, which is customarily divided into three stages (see Figure 21-4).
The first stage begins when spaced uterine contractions of sufficient frequency, intensity, and duration are attained to bring about cervical thinning, termed effacement.
Several uterotonins may be important to the success of this stage of active labor (see Fig. 21-5).
These have been shown to stimulate smooth muscle contraction through G-protein coupling.
This labor stage ends when the cervix is fully dilated—about 10 cm—to allow passage of the term-sized fetus.
The first stage of labor, therefore, is the stage of cervical effacement and dilation.
The second stage begins when cervical dilation is complete and ends with delivery.
Thus, the second stage of labor is the stage of fetal expulsion.
Last, the third stage begins immediately after delivery of the fetus and ends with the delivery of the placenta.
This stage of labor is the stage of placental separation and expulsion.
# First Stage: Clinical Onset of Labor.
Uterine Labor Contractions In some women, forceful uterine contractions that effect delivery begin suddenly.
In others, labor initiation is heralded by spontaneous release of a small amount of blood-tinged mucus from the vagina.
This extrusion of the mucus plug that had previously filled the cervical canal during pregnancy is referred to as “bloody show.
Its passage indicates that labor is already in progress or likely will ensue in hours to days.
Unique among physiological muscular contractions, those of uterine smooth muscle during labor are painful.
Suggested causes are: (1) hypoxia of the contracted myometrium—such as that with angina pectoris; (2) compression of nerve ganglia in the cervix and lower uterus by contracted interlocking muscle bundles; (3) cervical stretching during dilation; and (4) stretching of the peritoneum overlying the fundus.
Of these, compression of nerve ganglia in the cervix and lower uterine segment by the contracting myometrium is an especially attractive hypothesis.
Paracervical infiltration with local anesthetic usually produces appreciable pain relief with contractions .
Uterine contractions are involuntary and, for the most part, independent of extrauterine control.
Neural blockade from epidural analgesia does not diminish their frequency or intensity.
In other examples, myometrial contractions in paraplegic women and in women after bilateral lumbar sympathectomy are normal but painless.
Mechanical stretching of the cervix enhances uterine activity in several species, including humans.
This phenomenon is the Ferguson reflex .
Its exact mechanism is unclear, and release of oxytocin has been suggested but not proven.
Manipulation of the cervix and “stripping” the fetal membranes are associated with a rise in blood levels of prostaglandin F2α metabolites.
The interval between contractions narrows gradually from approximately 10 minutes at the onset of first-stage labor to as little as 1 minute or less in the second stage.
Periods of relaxation between contractions, however, are essential for fetal welfare.
Unremitting contractions compromise uteroplacental blood flow sufficiently to cause fetal hypoxemia.
In activephase labor, the duration of each contraction ranges from 30 to 90 seconds and averages 1 minute.
Contraction intensity varies appreciably during normal labor.
Specifically, amnionic fluid pressures generated by contractions during spontaneous labor average 40 mm Hg, but vary from 20 to 60 mm Hg .
Distinct Lower and Upper Uterine Segments During active labor, the anatomical uterine divisions that were initiated in phase 2 of parturition become increasingly evident (Figs. 21-11 and 21-12).
By abdominal palpation, even before membrane rupture, the two segments can sometimes be differentiated.
The upper segment is firm during contractions, whereas the lower segment is softer, distended, and more passive.
This mechanism is
imperative because if the entire myometrium, including the lower uterine segment and cervix, were to contract simultaneously and with equal intensity, the net expulsive force would markedly decline.
Thus, the upper segment contracts, retracts, and expels the fetus.
In response to these contractions, the softened lower uterine segment and cervix dilate and thereby form a greatly expanded, thinned-out tube through which the fetus can pass.
Figure 21-11.
Sequence of development of the segments and rings in the uterus at term and in labor.
Note comparison between the nonpregnant uterus, the uterus at term, and the uterus during labor.
The passive lower uterine segment is derived from the isthmus, and the physiological retraction ring develops at the junction of the upper and lower uterine segments.
The pathological retraction ring develops from the physiological ring.
Anat. I.O. = anatomical internal os; E.O. = external os; Hist. I.O. = histological internal os; Ph.R.R. = physiological retraction ring.
Figure 21-12.
The uterus at the time of vaginal delivery.
The active upper segment retracts around the presenting part as the fetus descends through the birth canal.
In the passive lower segment, there is considerably less myometrial tone.
The myometrium of the upper segment does not relax to its original length after contractions.
Instead, it becomes relatively fixed at a shorter length.
The upper active uterine segment contracts down on its diminishing contents, but myometrial tension remains constant.
The net effect is to take up slack, thus maintaining the advantage gained in expulsion of the fetus.
Concurrently, the uterine musculature is kept in firm contact with the uterine contents.
As the consequence of retraction, each successive contraction commences where its predecessor left off.
Thus, the upper part of the uterine cavity becomes slightly smaller with each successive contraction.
Because of the successive shortening of the muscular fibers, the upper active segment becomes progressively thickened throughout first- and second-stage labor (see Fig. 21-11).
This process continues and results in a tremendously thickened upper uterine segment immediately after delivery.
Clinically, it is important to understand that the phenomenon of upper segment retraction is contingent on a decrease in the volume of its contents.
For this to happen, particularly early in labor when the entire uterus is virtually a closed sac with only minimal cervical dilation, the musculature of the lower segment must stretch.
This permits a greater portion of the uterine contents to occupy the lower segment.
The upper segment retracts only to the extent that the lower segment distends and the cervix dilates.
Relaxation of the lower uterine segment mirrors the same gradual progression of retraction.
In the lower segment, successive lengthening of the fibers with labor is accompanied by thinning, normally to only a few millimeters in the thinnest part.
With lower segment thinning and concomitant upper segment thickening, a boundary between the two is marked by a ridge on the inner uterine surface—the physiological retraction ring.
When the thinning of the lower uterine segment is extreme, as in obstructed labor, the ring is prominent and forms a pathological retraction ring.
This abnormal condition is also known as the Bandl ring, which is discussed further in Chapter 23 (p. 442).
Changes in Uterine Shape Each contraction gradually elongates the ovoid uterine shape an estimated 5 to 10 cm and thereby narrows the horizontal diameter.
This fetal axis pressure straightens the fetal vertebral column.
It also presses the upper pole of the fetus firmly against the fundus, whereas the lower pole is thrust farther downward.
With uterine lengthening, the longitudinal muscle fibers are drawn taut.
As a result, the lower segment and cervix are the only parts of the uterus that are flexible, and these are pulled upward and around the lower pole of the fetus.
Ancillary Forces After the cervix is dilated fully, the most important force in fetal expulsion is
produced by maternal intraabdominal pressure.
Contraction of the abdominal muscles simultaneously with forced respiratory efforts with the glottis closed is referred to as pushing.
The force is similar to that with defecation, but the intensity usually is much greater.
The importance of intraabdominal pressure is shown by the prolonged descent during labor in paraplegic women and in those with a dense epidural block.
Cervical Changes As the result of contraction forces, two fundamental changes—effacement and dilation—occur in the ripened cervix.
For an average-sized fetal head to pass through the cervix, it must completely or fully dilate to a diameter of approximately 10 cm.
The fetus may not descend during cervical effacement.
However, as the cervix dilates, the presenting fetal part typically does descend somewhat.
Cervical effacement is “obliteration” or “taking up” of the cervix.
It is manifest clinically by shortening of the cervical canal from a length of approximately 3 cm to a mere circular orifice with almost paper-thin edges.
The muscular fibers at the level of the internal cervical os are pulled upward, or “taken up,” into the lower uterine segment.
The condition of the external os remains temporarily unchanged .
Because of growing myometrial activity during uterine preparedness for labor, appreciable effacement of a softened cervix sometimes is accomplished before active labor begins.
Effacement causes expulsion of the mucous plug as the cervical canal is shortened.
Figure 21-13.
Schematic showing effacement and dilation.
A. Before labor, the primigravid cervix is long and undilated in contrast to that of the multipara, which has dilation of the internal and external os.
B. As effacement begins, the multiparous cervix shows more dilation and funneling of the internal os compared with the primigravid cervix.
C. As complete effacement is achieved in the primigravid cervix, dilation is minimal.
The reverse is true in the multipara.
Because the lower segment and cervix have less resistance during a contraction, a centrifugal pull is exerted on the cervix and creates cervical dilation .
As uterine contractions cause pressure on the membranes, the hydrostatic action of the amnionic sac in turn dilates the cervical canal like a wedge.
The process of cervical effacement and dilation causes formation of the forebag of amnionic fluid.
This is the leading portion of fluid and amnionic sac located in front of the presenting part.
In the absence of intact membranes, the pressure of the presenting fetal part against the cervix and lower uterine segment is a similar wedge.
Early rupture of the membranes does not retard cervical dilation so long as the presenting fetal part is positioned to exert pressure against the cervix and lower segment.
Figure 21-14.
Hydrostatic action of membranes in effecting cervical effacement and dilation.
With labor progression, note the changing relations of the internal and external os in (A), (B), and (C).
Although not shown in this diagram, with membrane rupture, the presenting part, applied to the cervix and the forming lower uterine segment, acts similarly.
Referring back to Figure 21-4, recall that cervical dilation is divided into latent and active phases.
The duration of the latent phase is more variable and sensitive to extraneous factors.
For example, sedation may prolong the latent phase, and myometrial stimulation shortens it.
The latent phase duration has little bearing on the subsequent course of labor, whereas the characteristics of the active phase are usually predictive of labor outcome.
Normal and abnormal labor curves are fully described in Chapters 22 and 23.
# Second Stage: Fetal Descent.
In many nulliparas, engagement of the head is accomplished before labor begins.
That said, the head may not descend further until late in labor.
In the descent pattern of normal labor, a typical hyperbolic curve is formed when the station of the fetal head is plotted as a function of labor duration (see Fig. 21-4).
Station describes descent of the fetal biparietal
diameter in relation to a line drawn between maternal ischial spines .
Active descent usually takes place after dilation has progressed for some time.
During second-stage labor, the speed of descent is maximal and is maintained until the presenting part reaches the perineal floor .
In nulliparas, the presenting part typically descends slowly and steadily.
In multiparas, however, descent may be rapid.
# Pelvic Floor Changes.
The birth canal is supported and functionally closed by the pelvic floor .
The most important component of the floor is the levator ani muscle and the fibromuscular connective tissue that covers its upper and lower surfaces.
The biomechanical properties of these structures and of the vaginal wall change markedly during parturition.
These result from altered ECM structure or composition (Alperin, 2015; Lowder, 2007; Rahn, 2008).
In the first stage of labor, the membranes, when intact, and the fetal presenting part serve to dilate the upper vagina.
The most marked change consists of stretching levator ani muscle fibers.
This is accompanied by thinning of the central portion of the perineum, which becomes transformed from a wedge-shaped, 5-cm-thick tissue mass to a thin, almost transparent membranous structure less than 1 cm thick.
When the perineum is distended maximally, the anus becomes markedly dilated and presents an opening that varies from 2 to 3 cm in diameter and through which the anterior wall of the rectum bulges.
# Third Stage: Delivery of Placenta and Membranes.
This stage begins immediately after fetal delivery and involves separation and expulsion of the placenta and membranes.
Normally, by the time the newborn is delivered, the uterine cavity is nearly obliterated and is an almost solid mass of muscle, several centimeters thick, above the thinner lower segment.
The uterine fundus now lies just below the level of the umbilicus.
This sudden diminution in uterine size is inevitably accompanied by a decrease in the area of the placental implantation site .
For the placenta to accommodate itself to this reduced area, it thickens, but because of limited placental elasticity, it buckles.
The resulting tension pulls the weakest layer—decidua spongiosa—from that site.
Thus, placental separation follows the disproportion created between the relatively unchanged placental size and the reduced implantation site size.
Figure 21-15.
Diminution in size of the placental site after birth of the newborn.
A. Spatial relations before birth.
B. Placental spatial relations after birth.
Cleavage of the placenta is aided greatly by the loose structure of the spongy decidua.
As detachment proceeds, a hematoma forms between the separating placenta and the adjacent decidua, which remains attached to the myometrium.
The hematoma is usually the result rather than the cause of the separation, because in some cases bleeding is negligible.
The great decline in uterine cavity surface area simultaneously throws the fetal membranes—the amniochorion and the parietal decidua—into innumerable folds .
Membranes usually remain in situ until placental separation is nearly completed.
These are then peeled off the uterine wall, partly by further contraction of the myometrium and partly by traction that is exerted by the separated placenta as it descends during expulsion.
Figure 21-16.
Postpartum, membranes are thrown up into folds as the uterine cavity decreases in size.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Kelley S. Carrick.
After the placenta has detached, it can be expelled by increased abdominal pressure.
Completion of the third stage is also accomplished by alternately compressing and elevating the fundus, while exerting minimal traction on the umbilical cord.
The retroplacental hematoma either follows the placenta or is found within the inverted sac formed by the membranes.
In this process, known as the Schultze mechanism of placental expulsion, blood from the placental site pours into the membrane sac and does not escape externally until after extrusion of the placenta.
In the other form of placental extrusion,
known as the Duncan mechanism, the placenta separates first at the periphery and blood collects between the membranes and the uterine wall and escapes from the vagina.
In this circumstance, the placenta descends sideways, and its maternal surface appears first.
UTEROTONINS IN PARTURITION PHASE 3 # Oxytocin.
This nanopeptide is synthesized in the magnocellular neurons of the supraoptic and paraventricular neurons.
The prohormone is transported with its carrier protein, neurophysin, along the axons to the neural lobe of the posterior pituitary gland in membrane-bound vesicles for storage and later release.
The prohormone is converted enzymatically to oxytocin during transport (Gainer, 1988; Leake, 1990).
Oxytocin—literally, quick birth—was the first uterotonin to be implicated in parturition initiation.
Support for this role includes: (1) oxytocin receptor numbers strikingly rising in myometrial and decidual tissues near the end of gestation; (2) oxytocin acting on decidual tissue to promote prostaglandin release; and (3) oxytocin synthesis directly in decidual and extraembryonic fetal tissues and in the placenta (Chibbar, 1993; Zingg, 1995).
Moreover, abundant data support oxytocin’s important role during second-stage labor and in the puerperium, which is phase 4 of parturition.
Specifically, maternal serum oxytocin levels are elevated: (1) during second-stage labor, which is the end of phase 3 of parturition; (2) in the early puerperium; and (3) during breastfeeding .
Immediately after delivery of the fetus and placenta, which completes parturition phase 3, firm and persistent uterine contractions induced by oxytocin are essential to prevent postpartum hemorrhage.
# Prostaglandins.
Prostaglandins play a critical role in phase 3 of parturition .
First, levels of prostaglandins—or their metabolites—in amnionic fluid, maternal plasma, and maternal urine are increased during labor.
Second, receptors for PGE2 and PGF2α are expressed in the uterus and cervix.
Thus, if these tissues are exposed to prostaglandins, they will respond.
Third, treatment of pregnant women with prostaglandins, by any of several administration routes, causes abortion or labor at all gestational ages.
Moreover, administration of prostaglandin H synthase type 2 inhibitors to pregnant women will delay spontaneous labor onset and sometimes arrest preterm labor .
During labor, prostaglandin production within the myometrium and decidua is an efficient mechanism of activating contractions.
For example, prostaglandin synthesis is high and unchanging in the decidua during phase 2 and 3 of parturition.
Moreover, the receptor level for PGF2α is augmented in the decidua at term, and this increase most likely is the regulatory step in prostaglandin action in the uterus.
The fetal membranes and placenta also produce prostaglandins.
Primarily PGE2, but also PGF2α, are detected in amnionic fluid at all gestational ages.
As the fetus grows, prostaglandin levels in the amnionic fluid rise gradually.
Their greatest elevation in concentration within amnionic fluid, however, is demonstrable after labor begins.
These higher levels likely result as the cervix dilates and exposes decidual tissue .
These higher levels in the forebag, compared with those in the upper compartment, are believed to follow an inflammatory response that signals the events leading to active labor.
Together, the rise in cytokine and prostaglandin concentrations further degrade the ECM, thus weakening fetal membranes.
Figure 21-17.
Sagittal view of the exposed forebag and attached decidual fragments after cervical dilation during labor.
Redrawn from MacDonald PC, Casey ML: Preterm birth.
Sci Am 3:42, 1996.
# Endothelin 1.
The endothelins are a family of 21-amino-acid peptides that powerfully induce myometrial contraction .
The endothelin A receptor is preferentially expressed in smooth muscle, and when activated, it effects a rise in intracellular calcium.
Endothelin 1 is produced in myometrium of term gestations and is able to induce synthesis of other contractile factors such as
prostaglandins and inflammatory mediators (Momohara, 2004; Sutcliffe, 2009).
The requirement of endothelin 1 in normal parturition physiology remains to be established.
# Angiotensin II.
Modulation of uteroplacental blood flow is regulated by angiotensin II, a potent vasoconstrictor.
Although, in pregnancy, circulating levels of angiotensin II are increased, vascular resistance is reduced and vasodilation is enhanced.
Two angiotensin II receptors are expressed in the uterus—AT1R and AT2R.
In nonpregnant women, the AT1R receptor predominates, but the AT2R receptor is preferentially expressed in gravidas .
During normotensive pregnancy, AT2R-mediated effects on vascular smooth muscle lead to vasodilation, which contributes to the pregnancy-associated rise in uterine arterial blood flow.
Decreased AT2R expression is associated with preeclamptic pregnancies (Mishra, 2018; Rosenfeld, 2012) .
PHASE 4: THE PUERPERIUM Immediately and for about an hour after delivery, the myometrium remains persistently contracted.
This directly compresses large uterine vessels and allows thrombosis of their lumens to prevent hemorrhage.
This is typically augmented by endogenous and pharmacological uterotonic agents .
Uterine involution and cervical repair are prompt remodeling processes that restore these organs to the nonpregnant state.
These protect the reproductive tract from invasion by commensal microorganisms and restore endometrial responsiveness to normal hormonal cyclicity.
During the early puerperium, lactogenesis and milk let-down begin in mammary glands .
Reinstitution of ovulation signals preparation for the next pregnancy.
Ovulation generally occurs within 4 to 6 weeks after birth.
However, it is dependent on the duration of breastfeeding and lactation-induced, prolactin-mediated anovulation and amenorrhea.